<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Bits of Bytes</title><description>Your daily dose of Javascript knowledge</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><generator>Ghost 0.7</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2016 17:25:12 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>Hello World</title><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi all, welcome to my blog! Through this blog I want to share useful information about coding that I've found, interesting projects I've made, and general thoughts about life. Right now I'm learning the ins-and-outs of Javascript and its popular libraries like Node, Angular, and React. Javascript is a powerful&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/hello-world/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">809923c6-9835-48d5-afd1-86ff42a93d37</guid><dc:creator>Nick Olszowy</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2016 07:51:45 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Hi all, welcome to my blog! Through this blog I want to share useful information about coding that I've found, interesting projects I've made, and general thoughts about life. Right now I'm learning the ins-and-outs of Javascript and its popular libraries like Node, Angular, and React. Javascript is a powerful and flexible language, but has some quirks that take some practice to master (0 == false). Have no fear! This blog can guide you through these unknown waters of bits and bytes, and you'll be slinging code in no time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm from the Washington, DC area but currently living in the software engineering mecca of San Francisco. As I become more ingrained in the #techlife I hope to start blogging about cool ideas, promising  new technologies, and interesting startups too. Stay tuned for my first Javascript post!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>